YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Oversized Materials.
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Oversized Materials
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
Forms part of MS 324 UUID:b1fd47c5-118f-4db3-abcb-9c195b94ae65
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This record group includes oversized materials documeting the work of the YWCA from the 1890s to the present. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
A copy of the microfilmed records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records is available to borrow from the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith College via Interlibrary Loan.
To request the microfilm from our library you will need to submit the following information to your library's Interlibrary Loan department:
Author: Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. National Board
Title: Records, 1876-1970 [microform]
WorldCat Accession Number: OCLC 57415795
Notes: "Call # 689" and reel number(s) you want to borrow
Full descriptions and reel lists of the microfilm are available online.
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.
- BOXED ITEMS
  - Mounted posters 135th Anniversary, 1993-94 (Box 1129)
    [see also unmounted posters in flat file]
  - "Women First for 135 Years" art and design by Saul Bass (Box 1129)
  - Reproduction Poster Series I
    - Health and Fitness-Mother & Child ("Building for Health" by Marie Page) (Box 1129)
    - Health and Fitness-Swim ("Swim!" by Anita Parkhurst) (Box 1129)
    - Health and Fitness-The Gym ("Join the Gym," artist unknown) (Box 1129)
  - Reproduction Poster Series II
    - WWI Service-Marching Women Workers ("For Every Fighter a Woman Worker, Back Our Second Line of Defense" by Ernest Hamlin Baker) (Box 1129)
    - WWI Service-Care for Her ("For Every Fighter a Woman Worker, Care for Her Through the YWCA" by Adolph Treidler) (Box 1129)
    - YWCA Program-Foreign Born ("For United America, Division for Foreign Born" by C. Howard Walker) (Box 1129)
  - Reproduction Poster Series III
    - YWCA Program-Students of the World ("World Fellowship, the Students of the United States for the Students of the World" by Adolph Treidler) (Box 1129)
    - YWCA Program-Room Registry ("Call on Us if You Want Comfortable Accommodations," artist unknown) (Box 1129)
  - MOUNTED POSTERS, GENERAL (Box 1130)
    - "Forever Young and Brave," World Centennial, 1955 (Box 1130)
    - "They go to church, they go to school, they go to work, they go to the YWCA. Keep them going," 1950s (Box 1130)
    - "See the World in a New Light Through the YWCA" art by Fanuele, early 1960s and "Where You Can Belong," circa 1962 (Box 1130)
    - "The YWCA Belongs to You" [Asian woman, white woman], circa 1964 (Box 1130)
    - National YWCA Week designs, 1960s-early 1970s (Box 1130)
    - "Building a Better Community, Give to the World Through the YWCA" and "Say 'Yes' Give to the World Through the YWCA," undated (Box 1130)
  - "China develops her Co-operative Industries to aid her 60,000,000 Refugees" (Box 1130)
    [reduced size photocopy in box 60]
  - NAACP map "3436 Blots of Same on the U.S. 1889-1922" from Outline for a Discussion Course on Race Relations in the U.S. in box 538 folder 16 (Box 1131)
  - Photograph album, 600 Lexington Ave under construction and newly complete, exteriors and interiors, circa 1912-13 (Box 1131)
  - Looseleaf binder for YWCA Program Resources Organizers' Kits, 1990s (Box 1131)
  - Asilomar Inventory, 1942 (Box 1131)
    [reduced size photocopy available in box 227]
  - National YWCA Staff Design (proposed), 1971-72 (Box 1131)
    [reduced size photocopy in box 115]
  - The Augusta Courier, 12 Dec 1955 (Box 1131)
    [reduced size photocopy in box 179]
  - Interregional News Bulletin, spring 1956 (Box 1131)
    [reduced size photocopy in box 766]
  - Commemorative collection from dedication of Peace Site at the Leadership Development Center, 25 Aug 1987 (Box 1132)
- FLAT FILES
  - RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
    - Poster with revised Purpose statement, circa 1990 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - "Picture What Women Do" calendar 1995, published by Lifetime [YWCA featured in month of Mar] (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Posters with text of the YWCA Purpose, circa 1970s-90s (Box 61)
    - Anniversaries: World YWCA Centennial, 1955: posters, printed material; Resolutions from various states and cities, 1983, 1993; 135th Anniversary exhibit, information and layout; posters, 125th (1983) and 135th (1993) (Box 61, Folder 2)
    - Annual Reports: 1979-80, 1980-81 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Awards: certificates from various organizations, 1951-93 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Organization and committee structure charts, 1940-72 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Membership certificates, 1906, n.d. (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - 'Foreign' YWCAs (Box 61)
      - YWCA of China: Illustrations for Better Homes Campaign, Shanghai, 1921; "Itinerant Industries of China" from North-China Daily News Christmas Supplement [date in Chinese characters]; "Pictures of the City Centers" fold-out from Green Year Suppleme nt, Jul 1930; The China Press Sunday Pictorial Section, 24 Oct 1926; pictorial charts re women and work in Shanghai [date in Chinese]; miscellaneous unidentified items (Box 61, Folder 4)
      - YWCA of Egypt: souvenir "with our deep appreciation for your hospitality," n.d. Papyrus (?) with images of Goddess Isis leading queen Nefertiti into eternity and King Rameses II on his chariot of war, XIX dynasty (Box 61, Folder 4)
      - YWCA of Korea: map showing location of YWCAs; unidentified illustration (Box 61, Folder 4)
      - YWCA of Manila: certificate of recognition and appreciation to the YWCA of the USA, Oct 1951 (Box 61, Folder 4)
    - World YWCA posters, 1957, 1960, 1987, 1990, n.d. (Box 61, Folder 5)
  - RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
    - American Committee listing of YWCAs (from 1887 Annual Report) (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - National Board meeting minutes oversize attachments, 1927-42 (Box 62)
    - Board of Trustees meeting minutes oversize attachments, 1922-25 (Box 62, Folder 1A-B)
  - RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
    - SERIES I. GENERAL ADMINISTRATION
      - Controversy: press compilations related to "Behind the Lace Curtains," 1948 (Box 62, Folder 2)
      - Legal: proofs for Y-Teen patterns, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 2)
    - SERIES II. BUILDINGS AND PROPERTIES
      - Asilomar Conference Grounds (Box 62)
        - Map of 50 acre grounds, n.d. (Box 62, Folder 3)
        - Plan of Asilomar properties, 1917 (Box 46, Folder 1)
      - National Headquarters, 600 Lexington Ave., New York City: scale detail,counters in reception corridor and exhibition hall, 1913; Mail chute details, 1912; floorplans for National Board library renovation, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 3)
      - Leadership Development Center, Phoenix, Arizona: site plan, Clark/Van Voorhis Architects, 3 Jul 1981; partial floor plan, 1981; artwork for LDC information packets, n.d.; first anniversary poster, 1984 (Box 62, Folder 3)
    - SERIES III. FINANCE AND DEVELOPMENT
      - Comptroller's Office: documents re China property, 1919, n.d.; Grace Dodge Hotel registration chart, 1922 (Box 62, Folder 4)
      - Publications: flyers, charts, press spread, paid advertisement, 1940s-50s, 1985 (Box 62, Folder 4)
    - SERIES VI. PUBLICITY
      - Press clipping compilation "YWCA Speaks for White Collar Workers," 1942; National YWCA Week: 1946-47 press clipping compilations; JobCorps-YWCA spread in The Corpsman, 15 May 1970; YWCA Year at a Glance calendars, 1999-2000; "Stretch Out at the YWCA" newspaper guidelines, circa 1990s (Box 62, Folder 5)
    - SERIES VI. PUBLICITY (cont'd)
      - Posters
        - Photograph of 1952 National YWCA Week poster "On Our Own But Not Alone"; "Here's Your Cue to a Happier You" membership recruitment poster, 1950s?; "Come and Join!" membership recruitment poster, 1950s?; "Join and Look Ahead with the YWCA" public service poster distributed by Campbell Soup Co., featuring Donna Reed, circa 1960s; "There is no such thing as seeking God for there is nothing in which he could not be found, YWCA" green and white, circa 1970s; "Publicity Gives You Extra Program Push," 1978; "Celebrate a New Beginning" designed by Bass Yager Associations, 1980s (Box 62, Folder 6)
        - General publicity and membership recruitment, 1950s-early 1970s (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - RECORD GROUP 4. CONVENTION
    - Posters, ballots, credentials application blanks, flow charts of Convention process, exhibition hall layouts, 1910s-90s (Box 63, Folder 1-4)
    - Who's Who on the Ballot 1928, 1930, 1932, 1934, 1936, 1940, 1945 (Box 46, Folder 1)
    - Poster for 1926 Convention (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
    - Cartoon "World Fellowship Ahoy! The International Cruise of the Trusty Tub 'Goodwill' of the Salvation Navy" by Barbara Abel and Florence Nichols, published in the Womans Press, Sep 1927 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Photo spreads of American staff abroad printed in Association Monthly and Woman's Press, 1917 and 1949 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Awards certificates, 1971, n.d. (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Publicity flyers, 1956, 1959 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Posters
      - "Building a Better Community. Give to the World Through the YWCA," 1959; "The YWCA at Work in the World," 2 different versions, n.d.; "Our Share in the World (World Fellowship Giving)," n.d.; "Come Celebrate World Mutual Service Week," 1974 (Box 63, Folder 5)
      - "Behind the news are PEOPLE and those who try to help. YWCA Refugee Services," 1960s (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
    - SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES
      - Chart "Program in the YWCA" prepared by Bureau of Research and Program Resources, Apr 1963; Resource Center on Women prospectus and funding proposal, 1970 (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - SERIES II. PERSONNEL AND TRAINING
      - National Training School certificates, 1910-11 (Crissey McLemore), 1925 (Mildred Owen); Poster "Explore Career Opportunities in YWCAs Throughout the USA," n.d.; Financial reports for Career Volunteer Development Project, 1983 (Box 64, Folder 1)
    - SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY
      - Posters
        - "Conquer Fear of Insecurity and War by World Economic Co-Operation," and "Do You Remember Novemeber 11th? Permanent World Peace can be maintained by World Economic Co-operation," Campaign for World Economic Co-Operation, 1938 [distributed by YWCA]; "How the I.L.O. Works," International Labor Organization, 1939? [distributed by YWCA]; "Four Freedoms" series, 1944 [distributed by YWCA] (Box 64, Folder 2)
        - "Now is the Time" series, 1944; "Women's No. 1 War Duty," 1943-44 (Box 46, Folder 2)
        - "It's All the Same to Him," 1945 [blood plasma, distributed by YWCA]; Citizens Food Committee poster re conserving wheat and meat, 1947 [distributed by YWCA]; "Misinformation Vintage '49" [distributed by YWCA]; "Support the National Health Insurance Bill," circa 1950 [distributed by YWCA]; American Emergency Food Committee clippings collage poster, 1950-51 [distributed by YWCA]; "Your Vote is Your Voice," AFSCME, circa 1996 [distributed by YWCA]; 2 posters for United Nations Day, October 24, n.d. [distributed by YWCA] (Box 64, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous
        - U.S. Government Clip Sheet, George Washington Bicentennial Commission, 1932; Digest of official letters and communications regarding the Public Affairs Program, July 1945-1946; Articles: "Coast Japs are Interned in Mountain Camp," Life, 6 Apr 1942 and "The People Nobody Wants," n.d.; Reprint from Seventeen re Bretton Woods plan for cooperation in International Finance, 1945; Flyer: "The Colored Electorate Expects FEPC in '48"; Text of declaration of human rights, reprinted from Chicago Sun-Times, 11 Dec 1948; Statement by United States National Women's Organizations, 23 Jun 1952 [re United Nations Disarmament Commission]; News clippings collage, Status of Women, 1963; Press statement "A Call to Women Who Care," 1966; Chart: "Civil Rights and Land Development, background on housing for Negroes in Cleveland, Ohio," 1966 (Box 64, Folder 3)
      - Programs and Projects
        - Week Without Violence: posters, enlarged clippings, flyer layout, proclamation, 1996 (Box 64, Folder 3)
        - Women's Political Empowerment: poster series: "Most Politicians Still think women should be seen and not heard. In the last election 54 million women agreed," The Deciding Vote, Women's Vote [19]'96 (Box 46, Folder 2)
    - SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS
      - Subseries B. Immigration and Foreign Communities
        - Chart showing "the constituents of the population in cities of more than 100,000 inhabitants, 1920"; Flyer "America's Future Immigration Problem" published by the National Committee for Constructive Immigration Legislation, 1920; Diploma for Polish Gray Samaritan Training School, n.d. (Box 65, Folder 1)
      - Subseries C. Interracial/Racial Justice
        - Awards and proclamations: certificate of Merit, U.S. Public Health Service, 1949; National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1974; Office of the Mayor, City of Phoenix, 1990; Office of the Mayor, Washington, DC, 1993 (Box 65, Folder 1)
        - 3 press statements, Oct-Nov 1966: "A Call to Women Who Care";"Black Power" Statement by National Committee of Negro Churchmen; "Crisis and Commitment" (Box 65, Folder 1)
        - Poster/flyers for Institutes on the Web of Racism, 1970-72; "Elimination of Racism," One Imperative posters, circa 1971; Flyer "Some Highlights of Steps Along the Way to the One Imperative," 1979 and 1985; poster: "Simple Ways to End Racism," 1994; Reference materials Black Chronicle, circa 1970s (Box 65, Folder 1)
        - Poster "The YWCA Audits its Community to Break the Web of Racism," Center for Racial Justice, 1973 (Box 46, Folder 6)
      - Subseries D. Teen Age and Younger Girls
        - Posters: "The Girl Reserves of the YWCA. Help us put the Blue Triangle over the top!" Poucher, n.d. [mounted, torn]; "Girl Reserves, Ever Loyal, Ever Ready, Everywhere," Anita Parkhurst, n.d. [mounted, torn, many pin holes]; "In Service for the Girls of the World," Neysa McMein, 1919 (3) (Box 65, Folder 2)
        - Chart "Activities for the Girl Citizen,"1920s?; 3 Sample issues of The Girl Reserve Bookshelf to demonstrate the original format [photocopies filed in box 570], 1923-25; Girl Reserve Jubilee greetings from Estonia Girl Reserves, 1931; Collage of Girl Reserve Jubilee greetings from around the world, 1931; chart/poster, '"Teen-Agers" Keep Fit and Have Fun,' illustrations by Henrietta Wireman, USO Division (Box 65, Folder 3)
        - Posters: "Y-Teen Week, Teens for Peace, Teens for Justice, Teens for Freedom, Teens for Dignity…for all people. The YWCA is for Teens!" 1974(2); "Fuel YWCA Programs with Teen Energy, Join Y-Teens," n.d. (2); "Teen Women the Force is With You at the YWCA," n.d. (2) (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - SERIES V. PROGRAM SUBJECTS
      - Subseries A. Camping and Outdoor Recreation: flyer re Second National YWCA Conference on Outdoor Recreation and Conservation, Jul 1966 (Box 66, Folder 1)
      - Subseries B. Health and Recreation: Suggested "Skeleton" or "Back-Bone" Program for Constructive Health Programs through Standardized Clubs, Bureau of Social Education, 1920; Original artwork for ENCOREplus publications by Janet Hamlin, 1990s; "Get into the Game!" National Girls and Women in Sports Day poster, 1990s (Box 66, Folder 1)
      - Subseries C. Music Descant for "Goodnight, Beloved" by Lucy Schulte (Box 66, Folder 1)
      - Subseries E. Religion: chart "The Evolution of a Social Gospel," circa1951 (Box 66, Folder 1)
    - SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS
      - Woman's Press advertising stickers, n.d. (Box 66, Folder 2)
    - SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES
      - World War I
        - Special Peace Talk Newspaper Advertisements for the United War Work Campaign, 11-18 Nov 1918 (4); Reprint of New York Times cartoon "Ain't it a Grand and Glorious Feelin'?" by Briggs with text "The Men Know, Home Folks Know, YWCA Hostess Houses in Seventy Camps"; "A Miss Sehon, a l'occasion de son departtribute to Clarrette Sehon from "Les jeunes filles du Foyer," Bourges, 28 May 1920; "Card of Recognition" from Poland with thanks for food assistance to Polish children after World War I;Sheet music for "Get Behind the Girls Behind the Boys" music by Nat Goldstein, lyrics by Anita Day Downing. Official song of the YWCA Western Department, n.d. (Box 66, Folder 3)
        - Posters
          - "Back Our Girls Over There, United War Work Campaign YWCA," Clarence Underwood [operator, 1 copy unmounted, 1 copy mounted with glue spots]; "YMCA, Lend Your Strength to the Red Triangle. Help the Y Help the Fighters Fight," Gil Spear; "Joan of Arc Saved France. Women of America Save Your Country, Buy War Savings Stamps," Haskell Coffin, U.S. Treasury Department poster (Box 66, Folder 3)
          - "United We Serve," United War Work Campaign [no art] (2); fragments of a Neysa McMein United War Work Campaign poster; "How the Blue Triangle Helps in France" [small, bullet points, no art]; "Remember the Girl Behind the Man Behind the Gun, YWCA, War Work Council," M.B. [nurse bursting through blue triangle] (Box 66, Folder 4)
          - "The Girl on the Land Serves the Nation's Need," Edward Penfield (Box 46, Folder 3)
          - "For Every Fighter a Woman Worker," Adolph Treidler (3 copies); United War Work Campaign "United We Serve" (Box 46, Folder 4)
          - "For Every Fighter a Woman Worker," Ernest Hamlin Baker; "His Home Over There," Albert Herter [YM/YW] (Box 46, Folder 5)
      - World War II and Defense Services: Awards and certificates,1946-68; Press clipping compilations, 1941-42; War Community Services map, 1945; Bridgeport, Connecticut, Herald page re opening of USO building, 1942 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
    - 75th Anniversary spread in Woman's Press,1948; Membership certificates: Oberlin College YWCA, 1989, and Boise State University YWCA, 1991; Flyer re National Student YWCA, circa 1970s (Box 67, Folder 1)
- RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
  - Department/Division: Community Division poster "Why Support Your National Organization?" 1969 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - Community Associations files
    - Alabama: "Quiet Revolutionairies: The YWCA of Mobile" poster, 1989 (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - California
      - Hollywood Studio Club oversize clippings, 1950s; California Monthly cover story "Y's women," Feb 1989; "Legacy of Courage-YWCA Celebrates women in Orange County History," poster, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 2)
      - Survey of a portion of Block 11 Colegrove MR 53-10 at NW Corner of Lexington Ave & Lodi Place for Hollywood Studio Club, Julia Morgan, Architect [page from specifications in box 857. folder 6], 1925 (Box 67, Folder 2)
      - Oakland: plan for proposed remodeling, Warneke and Warneke, Architects, 1954 (Box 46, Folder 646)
    - Illinois: YWCA of Chicago(?) "Regulations of the Boarding House," n.d. [printed by Knight, Leonard & Co., Chicago] (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Iowa: Des Moines Sunday Register cover story re new YWCA building, 1971 (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Louisiana: Shreveport YWCA poster by Gary Cascio, n.d. (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - New York: YWCA of the City of New York flow chart showing relationships local to national to World YWCA, 1932 (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - New Jersey, Summit: Plot plan for proposed new addition, Ludlow and Jefferson, Architects, 1966 (Box 46, Folder 6)
    - Ohio: Cleveland YWCA Annual Report (poster format), 1981 (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Pennsylvania: reproduction of a mural-like pencil drawing with YWCA theme by Nick T. Ruggieri, Harrisburg, Pennsylvania YWCA, 1960s? (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified: "Where You Can Belong" series (YWCA, 5th and Seneca), n.d. (Box 67, Folder 2)
- RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Saturday Evening Post cover, 25 Mar 1944, "Gramercy Park" by John Falter showing #3, the first home of the YWCA National Training School (1908-summer 1913); Reception, National Association YWCA, Panama Pacific International Exposition, San Francisco, California, 18 May 1915; Group photo, International Institutes Conference, Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1926; Group photo, World's YWCA Council Meeting, Elgin House, Muskoka, Canada, Sep 1938; 3 enlargements of exhibition photographs: Y-Teens, National Industrial Progress Week, and World Fellowship ("The World We Build Rests on the Character We Build") (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified conference, Midwest, n.d.; Western City Conference, Hollister, MO, 1918; Southeast Regional Conference, Blue Ridge, NC, 1954; National Industrial Conference, silver Spring, MD, 1919 [2 different photos, 1 of them in pieces]; National Industrial Council, 1926; Blue Ridge Student Conference, 1912; Southeast Student YM and YW Conference, Hollister, MO, 1927, 1928, 1929; Foreign Division of YWCA of the U.S.A. and YWCA of Canada, 1929; World Council, 1938, 1955, 1967 (Box 46, Folder 7)
  - "O'Goshen" Girls Camp, Louisville, KY, YWCA, 1919 (Map-case flat file)
  - YWCA Conference, Kenilworth Inn, Asheville, NC, 1908 (Map-case flat file)
  - 5th National Convention, Los Angeles, CA, 1915 (Map-case flat file)
  - 29th National Convention, Washington, DC, 1982 (Map-case flat file)